They are so sophisticated and so far
advanced working with the likes of
Palunteer, Nvidia, all these cutting
edge tech companies. Couple what the CIA
was trying to do in the ' 50s with MK
Ultra and its subcomponents compared to
what it is technologically able to do
today and it is terrifying.
You mentioned this very briefly. We kind
of ran out of time in our last interview
where you said something along the lines
of like, you know, gone are the days of
just being able to cross borders and
alias and do a brush pass because
>> oh my god with with facial recognition
software and AI. I actually posed this
question to a current CIA officer. I
said, "How do you guys cross borders?
How do you get through airports like in
different in different uh names?" And he
said, "We don't know yet."
still struggling. Yeah, the technology
is developing so quickly, they just
can't keep up with it.
>> So, man, that that a lot of things are
running through my head right now, but
uh something I just thought of, I heard
from one of the science and technology
people that gave an interview that the
agency is involved in or dabbling in VR
and AR type stuff.
>> Oh, yeah. She didn't want to. She didn't
say what, but what would you like what
would you imagine that that's about?
>> Oh man. Um, I don't know because I've
been out a long time, but I will tell
you that the DS&T, the sorry, the the
Directorate of Science and Technology,
which is one of the four directorates at
the CIA
when I was there was almost an
afterthought because mostly what it was
responsible for was disguises
and um, you know, briefcases with secret
pockets in them and you know, supporting
operations. Now they are so
sophisticated and so far advanced
working with the likes of Palunteer
and Elon Musk's different companies and
AWS and all these like cutting edge you
know Nvidia all these cutting edge tech
companies they are so far advanced that
instead of doing the silly concealment
devices and disguises
they just pawn that off to, you know,
to, you know, individuals or or makeup
companies and and and they do the big
ticket items. Now, I would say what the
DS&T is doing with things like virtual
reality are closer now to what DARPA is
doing on futuristic tech than what they
ever did in the past at the CIA.
So, what would you say as an example?
Like, what would a big ticket item be in
that case?
Man, I you know what? I I couldn't even
venture to say it. I I don't even know.
It's become so sophisticated. I sat next
to a guy for years, awesome guy,
terrific analyst, and he always had a
thing for tech. We used to joke about it
cuz we were all young. When we were all
in our 20s, we're all techsavvy. Now
he's the CIA's chief technical officer.
SIS4,
he could be the director if the
president wanted him to be. And I
remember saying to a buddy of mine when
when our friend was promoted, I was
like, man, he really made it like to the
very top. And my friend said it was it
was the tech, you know, he I'll I'll
tell you what he did just as a favor on
his day off.
Um, he made a computer program
to allow our
Middle East analysts
to make family trees of the royal
families in the countries that they
cover, right? No such software existed.
There was no such thing as, you know,
family treemaker or genealogy.com. There
was no such thing as.com. I We're
talking about pre-in days. and he took
three days off on his own time and made
this program this software that
everybody in the office used. And I was
like, "Wow, he really knows a lot about
tech, huh?" And then two or three years
later, they invented the internet. Or
they didn't invent it then, but they
they released the internet to the
general public and he just jumped right
in and really really made something out
of himself. So, he's in charge of all
this stuff now. Yeah.
>> Did you ever have an experience with
DARPA?
>> Never. I was never cleared to even know
what it was they were doing over there.
They're so far advanced,
>> right? And that's what they say. They
say uh they say DARPA's
20 years ahead of what we can see.
>> Mhm.
>> And so I would think that
is the agency.
>> Yeah.
One of the things I learned early on at
the agency though is that it is far
cheaper and far easier to just buy
something that's already been invented
than it is to develop it from scratch.
That was before 9/11. Post 911, money is
not an issue at all. And so DARPA's
doing it, NSA's doing it, CIA's doing
it. And then they're with within QEL,
they're financing it uh in the public
sector. I'm sorry, in the private
sector.
So, the sky's is the limit, man. It
really is. And I can't even imagine the
Russians spending that kind of money on
tech. Maybe the Chinese do. I don't
know. They've got the money. But since
911, we've gone we've gone whole hog in
tech development.
>> Chinese could always just steal it from
us. I guess
>> they steal it from us. Yeah, just like
the Israelis do.
>> We'll talk about that.
>> We'll talk about Oh, we'll talk about
the MSAD, don't worry. Um,
>> Inkel is the the it's openly the CIA's
venture capital firm, right?
>> Correct.
>> Yeah.
and they're I want to say invest they
invested in Palunteer or
>> they gave Palunteer their first it was
like a million and a half to get off the
ground very first investment and now
look at Palunteer just this year for the
first time they have more than a billion
dollars in revenue so it's it's a
success story
>> so Palunteer does commercial stuff now
too it's not just um DoD and government
contracts
>> it's a standalone profitable tech
company
>> right So, they're selling to civilians,
so to speak. But, um, I remember when I
remember hearing when Palunteer first
came out that people at the agency
didn't like it
>> at all,
>> and maybe they gave him a trial run or
something and they were like, "Fuck
this. We don't want to use this." Yeah.
Do they use it now, you think?
>> Yeah.
>> What is it? What would they use it for?
>> Oh, all kinds of stuff. Mostly
mo Well,
you know what? I probably shouldn't say
I probably shouldn't say. Would it be
along the lines of targeting?
>> Yes.
>> Yes. You know, this this metadata has to
come from somewhere, right? So like with
Aviseda and remember Avisa was 23
years ago
where we're just laying out papers on
the ground and trying to connect the
dots. It's way more sophisticated now.
You can't get away now. You just can't
get away. So
rather than have analysts pouring over
this stuff and you just hoping that your
analysts are really really smart,
AI does it all. They do all of it
and it makes it much easier. That's why,
you know, that's why in the Obama
administration, John Brennan had the
Tuesday morning kill list meetings
because the tech got sophisticated
enough that you could just write up a
list of people that you want to kill
that week and you dish out the
assignments, the teams go out, they kill
everybody that's on the list, and then
they meet next Tuesday and get that kill
list. And you just do it week after
week. you know, when the when the Vault
7 uh documents were released back in
what was it 2017,
>> what are those?
>> Um there was a uh a CIA computer
engineer who named Joshua Schulty who
swears that he's innocent but is now
serving a sentence of 40 years for
espionage. He was apparently allegedly a
disgruntled engineer. He didn't like his
boss. He didn't like his co-workers.
They didn't like him.
So he just
downloaded the crown jewels of the
director of science and technology and
sent it all to Wikileaks in 2017. Google
Vault 7. Vault 7 documents. Vault 7
revelations. It will knock your socks
off.
Um thousands and thousands of pages. It
makes what Chelsea Manning leaked look
like, you know, scrawl from a sixth
grader.
So, he revealed that the CIA has
developed technologies to, for example,
remotely take over your car by hacking
into the chip, right? Why would the CIA
want to take over your car? To make you
drive off a bridge, maybe? To make you
drive into a tree and kill yourself? to
make you drive into an abutment and make
sure that there's no way you can survive
because they've got the thing going 140
miles an hour and you can't control it.
They developed technology to
to reverse your smart TV to make the
speaker into a microphone with the TV
still appearing to be off so you don't
know that it's broadcasting everything
that's being said in your house to CIA
headquarters.
you know, they were able to they were
able to hack into other count's um most
sensitive technological systems and to
leave little scraps of code, but the
scraps of code are written in Russian or
in Persian, in Farsy.
So people say, "Oh, the [__] Russians
hacked into us or the Chinese or the
Iranians." And actually, no, it it was
us, but you'll never know it.
I mean, there's almost too much in Vault
7 to even go into. It's incred. I'm
going to give a talk about it at at a
hacker conference this coming weekend.
So, um,
you know, couple what the CIA was trying
to do in the 50s with MK Ultra and its
subcomponents compared to what it is
technologically able to do today. And it
is terrifying.
Terrifying.
>> What's up, guys? Thank you so much for
taking the time to watch the interview.
If you got anything out of this video at
all, please like the video, leave me a
comment, tell me what you thought of the
video, uh, tell me who you'd like to see
on the show. I really appreciate the
support. It goes a long way on these
platforms, as you guys know. Most
importantly, I have some excellent
interviews coming up in the future that
I'm really, really excited about. So,
please subscribe to the channel so you
don't miss any of them. But that's it.
Thank you for your support.